This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
[music]
Welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
I'm your host, Gregory Kaphhammer.
Today's guests are Sam Goldman and Danny
Yang. Both Sam and Danny are software
engineers at Meta Platforms and they
work on the PyreFly project. Hey,
welcome to the show.
Hey Gregory, happy to be here.
Thanks for having us.
No problem, glad to chat with both of
you. Today our topic is PyreFly. PyreFly
is a type checker and it's a language
server for Python and it was built at
Meta and you've developed it and
open-sourced it and so we're going to
dive into some details. Now, to make
sure that we're on the firm footing at
the very start of the episode, Sam, if I
could turn to you, at a high level,
what's a type checker?
So, a type checker is uh part of the
software development process.
Programmers writing computer code, their
computer code might be written correctly
or incorrectly and a type checker is one
tool that programmers can use to find
errors in the code that they've written.
Okay. Now, many of our listeners may be
familiar with programming in Rust or in
Java and in those programming languages,
there is type checking that goes on but
it doesn't happen in an external tool.
So, Sam, can you develop that a little
bit further?
Yeah, so in the context of Python
specifically, a type checker is a tool
that someone needs to bring on
separately. So, Python does not come
with its own, well, static type checker
and so a tool like MyPy or PyreFly is
something extra that you would bring on
and use to find bugs in your code.
Okay, that's really helpful. Now, you
mentioned MyPy and we'll talk about MyPy
later in the episode, but Danny, if I
could turn briefly to you, I also
mentioned that Pyright Fly is a language
server. So, can you say a little bit
about what it means for it to be a
language server?
Yeah, a language server is a piece of
software that understands and conforms
to the language server protocol, which
allows it to communicate with various
different editors to provide IDE
features. For example, go to definition,
hover, code actions, things like that.
It's a common protocol so that you can
just implement one language server that
conforms to the specification and you
can have it work in VS Code, NeoVim, and
other editors like that.
Okay, so if I'm understanding you two
correctly, Pyright Fly is both a type
checker and an LSP. Is that the right
way to think about it?
Yes.
Okay, good. So, what we're going to do
at the beginning is talk a little bit
about some of the basics of Python type
checking, and then we're going to talk
about the design and implementation of
Pyright Fly, focusing on how you perform
type checking from an internal
perspective. We'll also talk about
details related to the performance of
Pyright Fly, but in order to get
started, since Pyright Fly is an add-on
to the Python programming language, when
do I use it? Where does it fit into my
overall workflow as a Python programmer?
So, you would use it while you are
writing code. So, a great way to use it
is say you use VS Code as your main IDE.
You can go right to the extension
marketplace, search for Pyright Fly, and
install it, and it will start working
right away. You will see the language
server behavior. You can get syntax
highlighting, you can jump to
definitions, and in the diagnostics
pane, type errors would appear as a
list, and you can navigate to the
location of the type error in your code.
So, that's one time where you would use
it. Another place where it's really
really common and a good idea to use
type checking is during CI, continuous
integration, testing that you would
perform for every change that goes into
your code base.
Okay, so I want to talk quickly about a
few different terms that we often hear
people mention when we talk about typing
and type systems. I know that typing
started in PEP 484 and that was many
years ago and that Python has something
that's called a type annotation. Can you
tell us a little bit, Danny, what is a
type annotation in the Python
programming language and how does it fit
into the workflow that Sam mentioned a
moment ago?
So, a type annotation is like some
special syntax that you write into your
Python program that lets you mark the
type of variables or functions, inputs
and outputs, attributes of classes,
things like that. So, when you run a
Python program normally, the Python
interpreter ignores the type annotations
and they don't really matter for
runtime, but the type checker will read
those annotations and check your code
based on that. So, the element of
standardization here is that Python has
standardized this way of providing
optional type annotations in your code
if you choose to do so and type checkers
should be able to understand those
annotations.
Okay, so as a Python programmer, I don't
have to put the types in my code, but if
I put the types there as annotations or
hints, they help Pyre flow to do a
better job. Is that the right way to
understand it, Danny?
Yes, even without annotations, a type
checker or language server will try its
best to analyze the code and do various
levels of type inference to guess the
types, but with concrete annotations,
typically the type checker performs
better.
Okay, actually that's really helpful.
You mentioned the word inference and
often when I learn about type checkers,
I remember reading about inference and
refinement. Can you briefly say what
those two terms mean, Danny?
So, Sam can correct me if he believes
differently, but in my mind, inference
is where we are guessing a type when the
type is not explicitly specified or
annotated. And refinement is a form of
inference because we are guessing a
narrower type based on the structure of
the code. So, for example, in a language
like Java, you might explicitly cast
things, but in Python, it's much more
common to assert some like structural
properties of the code. For example,
like this variable has you use has
attribute, or you check the length of a
tuple or something like that. And these
the type checker can understand to get
more information about the type, and
that's refinement.
Sam, do you want to dive in and share
any more details?
Yeah, I mean, Danny was absolutely
right. I think I want to add One more
thing on refinement and why it's so
interesting in the context of Python is
that Python by itself as a language is
not statically typed. So, the way that
people write Python code is a little bit
different from how you might write Rust
or C++. And as a result, the code that
we see and that we have to analyze
includes a lot of runtime type tests.
So, you might write a function that can
be called in a flexible way, maybe a
caller can pass a string or a number to
your function, and the function will
internally check, say, "Hey, is the
argument that I received a string? If
it's a string, I'll do one thing, and if
it's a number, I'll do something else."
And so, it's really important for
PyreFly to be able to follow that logic
in people's code, which is why you see
this refinement logic in type checkers
for dynamic languages like Python and
TypeScript, where it's much less common
or doesn't exist at all in languages
like Rust.
Okay, that's helpful. Now, I've heard
both of you mention the word static and
then also the word dynamic. And I know
in the context of programming languages
or software testing, we often talk about
static analysis and dynamic analysis.
So, where does type checking fit into
static analysis versus dynamic analysis?
So, well, type checking can appear in
both places, but for PyreFly, it's a
static type checker, which means that we
don't run any code. So, we don't get to
see what's happening when your program
runs. We are looking at the source code
before anything has happened.
Okay, so static analysis means you don't
run the program, you just study the
program's source code. Is that the right
way to think about it?
Yeah.
Okay, awesome. So, obviously, one of the
key goals of a type checker is that we
want to be able to find bugs in our
programs before we deploy them to
production. And I don't know who would
want to jump in here, but could one of
you share a concrete example or tell a
story of how type checking can actually
find a bug in a program?
So, I can give an example of like a
everyday thing that you would do in your
code base and how type checking can
help. So, for example, if you have a
function and you want to refactor it to
remove an argument, the type checker
would be able to give you an error at
every single call site of that function
and say, "Hey, you have to remove the
argument at all of those places." And
without it, you would have to grep
through the code base and find all the
call sites, but you might not find
everything because Python is pretty
dynamic, right? You can alias functions,
you can pass them around. It could be a
function that has a common name and
there's like other functions across the
code base that aren't actually the same
thing, but have the same name. So, the
type checker just makes that process a
lot easier and less error-prone.
Okay, I get it. Now, one of the things I
noticed is that there's many different
type checkers or LSP implementations in
the broader Python landscape. So, for
example, MyPy is a well-known type
checker, and then there are other things
that are LSPs like Pyright, and then
there's something else called Zubon,
which seems to be both a type checker
and a language server. So, I'm wondering
if the both of you could work together
to give our listeners maybe a broad
overview of the Python type checking and
LSP ecosystem. Can you help us out?
Yeah, I can give a high-level overview
here. So, you mentioned PEP 484, which
is the
PEP which introduced type annotations to
Python, and this came from MyPy. MyPy is
really the
originator of
typing in Python. So, MyPy is a great
piece of software. It's been around for
a long time. It is just a type checker.
It is not also a language server. It's
written in Python and pioneered a lot of
the ideas in this space. So, later on, I
don't know exactly when, but out of
Microsoft, there was the Pyright
project. And Pyright is a language
server and type checker. And I think
that the reason why Pyright became so
popular is that the language server
features provide so much value that it's
really
I think makes the value of type checking
connect with people in a really big way.
So, for a long time, the situation was
that you had MyPy as the type checker.
It had been around for years. People
were used to using it. But then people
also started using Pyright in the IDE
because the language services are so
powerful and useful. But it's a little
bit awkward because then you have one
type checker doing analysis for language
services, one type checker giving you
type errors. They might not always
agree, and it's a little bit of a
unfortunate situation. So, there's this
now a new school of type checker that's
coming out, Zovan, Typerfly,
that all
aim to be both highly efficient and
highly compatible. And so now it's a bit
of a I think inflection point in Python
typing because there's so many new
entries into the space that are all
trying to become the all-in-one
solution.
Okay, that makes sense. I know many of
our listeners may have used a type
checker before and they have worked on
it in certain cases where it found a bug
and then other cases where it flagged up
a problem and then it wasn't really a
problem. So, Danny, this leads me to my
next question. What are false positives
and false negatives and true positives
and true negatives in the context of a
program like Pyreflly?
Yeah, so since Pyreflly is a static type
checker, it doesn't have access to the
information at run time and run time
values. And to a certain extent, it's
essentially like reading the code and
trying to guess the programmer's intent,
especially when there are no
annotations. So, there are cases when
you can guess wrong. So, I would say a
true positive is when Pyreflly flagged
an error and it was actually a bug. A
true negative is when there's no error
and there's no bug. A false positive is
if Pyreflly got confused somehow by the
program and flagged an error when there
was actually no bug and the code is
actually fine. And then a
false negative would be like if there
actually is a bug, but somehow it was
not caught.
Thank you. So, now my next question is
perhaps deceptively simple, but I'm
hoping you can tackle it as well. What
does it mean if a program passes a type
checker? So, if I run Pyre fly check in
my terminal window and it doesn't give
me anything to look at, what do I know
about my program?
It means that from Pyre fly's
perspective, the program and the type
annotations are consistent with each
other.
Okay, I get it. Now, the next thing I
wanted to develop, and I'm hoping
perhaps Sam, you can help me here, is
that I've used multiple type checkers on
the same project. And often times, but
not always, they will actually flag up
different types of messages. Can you
help our listeners understand why
different type checkers might actually
flag different concerns about the same
Python program?
Yeah, that's a great question. So, there
are a lot of different reasons why that
might happen, but I think the biggest
difference would be choices that the
type checkers have made about how much
to infer, how much to leave untyped, and
then also just how complete of an
implementation the type checker has of
the typing specification.
Okay, so they might disagree, and then
I'm going to have to do my diligence in
order to discover which one seems to
line up best with the PEP specification
for typing, and then maybe look at both
of them and then as a developer make an
educated decision on what to do next. Is
that the kind of workflow?
Yeah, and I would say that it's not a
great workflow. So, I don't think it's
really a good place to be for the
ecosystem to have multiple type checkers
that all disagree in significant ways.
Hopefully, if you have an experience
like this where you're using two or more
type checkers and they don't give you
the same exact advice, then at least all
the advice you get will be useful.
It's possible that maybe you're using
multiple different type checkers and you
get some type checkers have false
positive, which is really not useful, or
a type checker has a false negative
where it's like, "Hey, MyPy caught this,
but Pyright didn't. Why not?"
Okay, I see what you're getting at. So,
to summarize really quickly, I think
you're saying that both false positives
and false negatives are things that we
would like to avoid when we're building
a type checker, and that true positives
and true negatives are both good things
when we're building a type checker. Did
I catch that the right way?
Yeah, absolutely. And when we are
working on PyreFly, we really look
closely at false negatives and false
positives. It's one of the main things
that we track from release to release.
Did we increase the amount of false
positives or false negatives? If so, we
have to follow up and investigate that.
So, we look at a corpus of real-world
code as we develop to see how we're
performing.
Okay, that makes sense. Now, one of the
things I wanted to talk about next is
the idea of gradual typing. And
additionally, I know that the Python
programming language supports something
that's called the any type. Danny, can
you help the listeners to understand
gradual typing and the use of something
called any?
Yeah, so I guess the any type is a type
that says the value can literally be
anything in a very permissive way. If
you have something that's any type, you
can pass it into a function regardless
of whatever type it takes. You can do
whatever operations you want with it,
and it's just signals to the type
checker that we have no good information
about this type. So, the type checker
will treat it as compatible with
anything, and that allows us to not give
a lot of false positive errors when we
actually don't know anything about the
type.
Okay.
If you use it as an explicit annotation,
you can view it as like a backdoor,
like, "Oh, this thing is too hard to
type. Let's give it an any." That's one
way to use it, but also internally, the
type checker will infer any in places
where it doesn't know. Like for example,
if you annotate something with just list
with no type arguments, then it'll it
has to guess a list of any's.
Okay, I see what you're getting at. Now,
I wanted to take a little bit of time to
read one quotation, and I saw this on
the PyreFly website, and then I'd like
to develop the idea of performance after
I read the quotation. So, PyreFly's
website says that it can type check over
1.85 million lines of code per second on
Meta's infrastructure. And I have to
say, Sam, that's an incredible number.
It's nearly 2 million lines of code per
second. So, can you tell our listeners,
why is performance so critical for type
checkers?
Well, I would say that performance is
critical for all of our developer tools.
I think everyone enjoys when their tools
are fast. And then, not just fast, but
there's a moment when a tool responds
instantaneously. And I think at that
moment,
a tool can really transform, where you
don't think about using it, you can
integrate it on every keystroke, and it
becomes very conversational. And so,
that was one of our goals for PyreFly.
That makes a lot of sense. And in fact,
you used the word conversational, and it
makes me think about using a tool like
Cloud Code or Open Code. I'm guessing
that performance is also really critical
in the context of agentic software
engineering. Sam, can you develop that a
little bit further?
Yeah. So, for the last several months,
the industry has changed significantly,
and we have been trying to adapt with
those changes ourself. So, it's really
interesting, and I think the story is
not quite told, but it's true that if an
agent can use a type checker like
PyreFly as a tool, and get better
information, then it can help the
trajectory of that agent interaction be
better, tend towards success, because
the agent can verify at every step. And
that the more it can verify and the more
cheaply it can verify, the fewer tokens
you use and the faster your interaction
is with that agent.
Okay, so in a way PyreFly can guide the
agent towards a correct Python
implementation because it's flagging
type checking errors, giving that
directly back to the agent, which passes
it along to the LLM, and then in a tight
loop you can find bugs more rapidly
because of the fact PyreFly is so
efficient. Did I summarize that workflow
in the right way, Danny?
Yeah, it's very similar to how a human
programmer would use a type checker,
too, right? It tightens the feedback
loop. It shifts errors left. You can see
both a human and an AI, in absence of a
type checker, maybe they would run the
full test suite of the program to verify
that their change is correct and sit
around for several minutes waiting for
the tests to run. But instead, with the
type checker, they would be able to get
updated signals on every keystroke or
every file save. And that's like a very
powerful thing.
Okay, I've got it. Now, what I want to
do next is talk about how you actually
built PyreFly. And I know PyreFly was
built in Rust, so I'd like to talk
briefly about your decision to use Rust
over other programming languages. Could
both of you help our listeners out? Why
did you pick Rust for PyreFly?
So,
we chose Rust for a few reasons. I think
it helps to get into a little bit of the
history of our team because this team
had previously built software called
Pyre. So, PyreFly is the successor to
Pyre. And Pyre was written in OCaml,
which is a pretty niche functional
programming language that's popular with
academics and also popular with
programming language enthusiasts. And I
love OCaml. So, I love writing in OCaml
and I've done it for the last decade.
But Rust was really a great choice for
us because we wanted to build a big open
community. And OCaml has a much smaller
developer population, whereas Rust is
very popular. People who don't already
know Rust are interested in learning
Rust, and a lot of people know Rust.
Another big reason for our choice is the
just sheer quantity of high-quality
third-party code that we can pull in
use.
Okay, that's really helpful. Now, since
we know a little bit about why you
picked Rust, I know that it's connected
to Pyre, but you didn't actually reuse
any of the code from Pyre inside of your
implementation of PyreFly. Did I
remember that correctly?
Yes, PyreFly is a spiritual successor.
It doesn't reuse any of the
implementation of Pyre, but a lot of the
lessons and designs from Pyre sort of
influenced how we designed PyreFly. So,
we took some of the things that were
good from it, and also things that Pyre
couldn't do that we wanted to make sure
PyreFly could do, and try to learn
lessons from where Pyre really couldn't
scale as well performance-wise and
things like that.
Okay. Now, my next question is going to
paint with a very broad brush, but with
that initial comment out of the way, I'm
going to say what I would call the three
phases of PyreFly. So, in phase one, you
have to figure out what each module
exports or imports, and you have to
solve imports transitively. In phase
two, you have to convert modules to
bindings, and you have to take into
account something called scope. And then
in phase three, you essentially have to
solve those bindings. Now, I recognize
it's much more complicated than that,
but if I summarize it in terms of those
three phases, could the two of you now
work together and talk our listeners
through those three phases in greater
detail?
Yeah, I think that the way you described
it is definitely correct, but the first
place I would maybe zoom out to is going
from one file to many files. So, if
we're just talking about one file, then
yeah, we parse into an AST, we turn the
AST into an intermediate representation
that we call bindings, which represents
the AST after scope resolution has been
done. So, if you use a variable name,
where is the definition of that name?
And then we go through this process of
solving the bindings. And
the bindings form a graph and the
solution step is walking that graph,
doing analysis along the way. The reason
it's built that way is for laziness. So,
this is when we zoom out from a single
file, we're in maybe a large project
with hundreds or thousands of files.
PyreFly is different from other tools in
that it's designed as a language service
first. If we were just building a type
checker, we'd build it very differently
where we would find all the files, we
would do for all the files in this batch
processing mode. But when you build an
LSP first, you actually have to turn
that whole process inside out. And this
is where a lot of the key design
decisions come in. Having this graph
that can be lazily elaborated. So, you
start by someone opens a file in the
IDE, and you want to be able to give
them useful information within
milliseconds. So, you can't even spend
time walking the whole file tree to
discover what all the files are. You
need to start from an entry point and
expand out incrementally.
Thanks, that was both helpful and
compelling. Now, a moment ago I
mentioned the idea of solving imports in
a transitive fashion. Danny, could you
define the meaning of transitivity in
the context of PyreFly and type
checking?
So, when one file depends on another, it
can be direct, which is like, okay,
module A imports module B, but it can
also be like a transitive thing. For
example, module A imports a class from
module B, and that class has a field
that's typed using a class defined in a
module C. So, then module A has like a
transitive dependency on the module C.
Okay, that's helpful. And then Sam, I
remember a moment ago you were talking
about how you turn it inside out when
you look at it from an LSP perspective.
So, can you tell us maybe from an LSP
perspective, what's the scope
information that PyreFly uses? And in
particular, what is scope in the context
of a programming language?
Yeah, so scope in the context of a
programming language is really a simple
idea and it's mapping of from names to
definitions is I think the easiest way
to think about it. And it's something
that developers have in their head at
any given time, but when we talk about
analysis and the algorithms to perform
that analysis, we, you know, we make
scope specific concept. So, if you're in
a function and the function takes two
parameters X and Y and you add them
together, you have this expression in
your function X plus Y. You know, what
does X mean? What does Y mean? The fact
that those names map to the parameters,
that's what we would include in scope.
Okay, I got it. Now, I'm wondering if
you could tell our listeners maybe a key
technical challenge you faced when it
came to building PyreFly or perhaps a
story you could tell about improving the
performance or the correctness of the
tool. Does anything jump to mind?
I can think of one and it gets to this
core idea of laziness. So, when you open
a file, we will analyze that file, but
we also might need to get information
from the files that you import and then
transitively from the files that those
files import and so on and so on. So,
early in the design of PyreFly, we knew
that we had to support this kind of
laziness, but we didn't always get it
right all the time. So, one of the bugs
that we fixed early on was that whenever
you imported a file, we would eagerly
analyze that entire file, which meant
that if you had a project with a lot of
third-party code, sometimes you had a
project that had maybe two or three
files in it, but through its
dependencies, the third-party libraries
would have millions of lines of code.
And to type-check those files, it took
sometimes over a minute when it should
have taken just a few milliseconds. So,
we had to increase the laziness in key
places so that we didn't end up
analyzing all of the third-party
dependencies.
Aha, I get it. So, if I'm a programmer
and I'm using Django or I'm using
FastAPI, you have to be careful from the
perspective of laziness. If I import
FastAPI, maybe you're not going to check
everything inside of FastAPI right away.
You just check the parts that it looks
like I'm most likely to use. How do you
decide when you have to like overcome
your laziness and start to analyze my
imports?
So, we have a indexing job that runs
when the language server first starts.
So, in addition to this like fully lazy
initial initial load that gets you
information in the first file that you
open, we also have something running in
the background that indexes your project
and sort of all the third-party
dependencies that it includes. And that
happens in the background and takes, you
know, several seconds, but once that's
done, then everything like fully works.
But initially, when it first loads, you
you already have something working while
Pyright is working in the background to
solve the rest.
Okay, that makes a lot of sense. Now,
when I was doing some research about
type checking for Python, I remember
coming across something that was called
typeshed. Does Pyright use typeshed and
ultimately, how does this idea of a
third-party stub play into the idea of
type checking?
Typeshed is a repository of type stubs
for various third-party packages that
don't have inline type annotations. This
can be for, you know, historical
backwards compatibility reasons like,
oh, maybe the package needs to work with
like older versions of Python that don't
have typing, but sometimes maintainers
just don't want the trouble of
maintaining maintaining type annotations
either. But for whatever reason, like
typeshed is a sort of centralized place
that stores these type stubs for
third-party packages, and PyreFly uses
them by bundling some of the type stubs
to provide, you know, better IDE
behavior out of the box. But if you're
writing a Python project, you can also
like add these type stub from PyPI as
one of your dependencies, and that way
no matter which type checker or language
server you use, it will know about the
types.
Okay, so the way that I'm thinking about
is that typeshed is providing type
annotations if a project doesn't
natively provide the annotations. Is
that the right idea?
Yeah, that's right.
Okay, awesome. So, I know a while ago
you mentioned the idea of hovering, and
you talked about go to definition, and
my understanding is that those are all
things that happen inside of the IDE.
So, could one of you tell me like
overall, what are the things that would
happen in my IDE, and then what are the
types of things that would happen in a
CLI, or in an agent coding harness, or
in CI/CD? Can you walk us through that
whole landscape?
Yeah, so in an IDE, it's very common to,
you know, you're reading code, you're
writing code, you're navigating. You
might type class and then a dot.
And from the dot, you want to access a
method or a field from that class. So,
what PyreFly and other language servers
can can do is give you a list of here
are all the things that you can access
from that class. So, that's something
that you would do while you're writing
code. It's an authoring action, we would
say. Other actions are less about
authoring and more about navigation. So,
maybe you say you're reading some code
and you see a reference to a class. You
say, "Well, what is this class? What
does it do?"
Or function call. You what you can do is
you can command click or control click
on that name in the code and PyreFly
will navigate will open the file and
navigate to the line where that
definition exists in the code. You can
go and read it. So, those are actions
that you would do in navigating or
authoring code in the IDE. In the CLI,
the
dominant interface is give me the list
of all the type errors at this moment.
So, you would run PyreFly check
and it would read the code and just give
you a list of type errors that you could
then, you know, look at and decide which
one you want to fix first.
Okay, I see what you're getting at. Now,
just briefly to make sure our listeners
are clear. So, this means that you can
use it in VS Code or NeoVim or Zed and
then you can also run it in your
terminal window or in an agent harness.
I think that you can just do something
like pip install PyreFly or UVX PyreFly
check. Am I understanding that the right
way?
Yes, that's how you would run it on the
command line. In VS Code, you would go
to, I guess, the VS Code extension
marketplace and just download the
PyreFly extension, which automatically
launches a PyreFly as a language server
when you open a Python file. And for the
unofficial VS Code forks, you would go
to the open VSX marketplace, which is
similar.
Okay. Now, many of our listeners may
already be using MyPy or Pyright. Like,
they might have Pyright running in their
IDE and maybe they're running MyPy on
the command line. So, can you give them
some advice if they want to migrate from
MyPy or Pyright to start using PyreFly?
What should they do?
So, PyreFly actually provides some
migration utilities that help when
you're trying to switch type checkers.
[snorts] So, I guess at its core it just
looks at any existing MyPy or Pyright
configuration file for your project and
it tries to generate a Pyreflly
configuration file that has roughly the
same settings. So, the error codes are
not like one-to-one, but we try our best
to like provide mappings between MyPy
and Pyright's error codes and ours. Like
different levels of inference, like
Pyreflly has a bit more inference than
Pyright has, for example. So, in our
migration from Pyright, we actually turn
off some of that inference to make it
more compatible. And then if you want to
sort of increase the strictness later
on, you can. And another aspect of
migration is because these type checkers
have sort of different behaviors for the
non-standardized parts of the type
system, sometimes it's going to be rare
when you're switching from one type
checker to another and you get a
completely clean check for your first
time. So, another utility that we
provide is called Pyreflly suppress,
which suppresses all of the existing
errors in your code base. And that makes
the initial migration process easier.
And then you would just clean up the
suppression comments later on. Or if you
didn't want the suppression comments in
your code base, you could set it aside
in a baseline file, which is what we
provide. So, it's it's just a text file
that on the side that lists all of the
type errors that Pyreflly currently
emits. And all of those Pyreflly can
read that and suppress them without
needing to insert a bunch of comments
one by one.
Okay. Thanks for sharing that about the
suppress approach. I wasn't aware of it,
but I can definitely see how it would be
useful. Now, I know many Python
programmers actually put lots of
configuration for their project inside
of the pyproject.toml
file. Can you configure Pyreflly using
pyproject.toml?
Yes.
Okay, that's helpful. Now, a moment ago
and also quite a bit earlier in the
show, we talked about the idea of
inference. And I know in addition to
PyreFly check and PyreFly suppress,
there's also something called PyreFly
infer. Can you develop that a little bit
further and then say in a practical way,
how does PyreFly infer help me as a
Python programmer?
So, PyreFly infer is a tool that fills
in a gap that PyreFly check has by
design. So, part of the design of
PyreFly is that the inputs to functions
are not inferred. So, if you have a
function which takes some number of
parameters and those parameters have no
type annotation on them, PyreFly treats
them like the any type that we discussed
earlier. So, any use is not checked for
errors. And this is a really important
part of PyreFly's design because
inferring the type of a parameter is
quite difficult. It requires looking
everywhere that that function is called,
which could be at anywhere in the
program. And for libraries, it might not
even be in your code repository at all.
It could be some dependent, you know,
library in another repo. So,
we make the choice, following existing
type checkers, to not infer those types.
What PyreFly infer does is a slower kind
of one-time or kind of occasionally run
analysis that looks at all the uses of
functions, both parameters both within a
function and from callers, and says,
"You you probably want to have this
annotation." So, it's a way to bootstrap
typing for an untyped project. Where if
you have functions with untyped
parameters, PyreFly infer will suggest
what those probably should be.
Now, I just wanted to connect this to
something we talked about before. We
said there's static analysis and dynamic
analysis. Is PyreFly infer static or
dynamic analysis?
PyreFly infer is totally static. There
are other tools that you can use. I'm
not as familiar. I believe one is called
MonkeyType, where you can run your
program and it will do at runtime
tracing of the values that come in
through functions. And you can then use
that.
Okay. Yeah, I remember Python's
MonkeyTyping tool, and I've actually
used it by running my Pytest test suite,
and then letting MonkeyType infer
through a dynamic analysis what it
thinks my types are. But, if I'm
catching you correctly, Pyre infer is a
completely static process.
Yeah, that's right.
Okay. Now, I wanted to quickly
double-click on issues that are related
to performance, because you've mentioned
this idea of laziness. And then also,
Danny, you talked about how when the LSP
is running, it's like running in the
background and doing checks for me, so
that when I want to infer something down
the road, it can help me out. So, I know
that your documentation says that it's
like a lightning-fast approach for
auto-complete, or that it has instant
feedback, so that it can catch errors.
So, what I'd like to unpack is the
secret sauce associated with making it
really fast, besides the laziness that
we've talked about. Can you two help us
out? What is it that makes PyreFly so
fast?
I think, you know, one area where we
spend a lot of time is parallelism. So,
MyPy is written in Python, and because
of Python's global interpreter lock, it
is single-threaded.
And Pyright, written in TypeScript, so
running on a JavaScript engine, also a
single-threaded kind of environment by
default. Rust allows us to write very
parallel analysis. So, we can use all of
the CPU cores on your machine to do
analysis. And this is how we achieve
this, you know, staggering lines per
second metric. We, in the indexing phase
that Danny mentioned are able to chunk
up the work and do it in parallel across
many cores.
Okay, that makes a lot of sense. So,
parallel processing helps you to be much
more faster. Do you have something in
your own development workflow that helps
you to like catch performance
regressions inside of PyreFly? And if
so, how do you handle that process?
We have some CI jobs that measure the
performance along several different
metrics. So, end-to-end like type
checking time on a project is one thing,
but there's also in the language server
for example, when you first open a file,
how long does it take to index? Also,
when you make an edit, how fast is the
incremental edit time? So, it's like if
you make an edit in one file and you
have another file that depends on it,
like how quickly do the errors in your
second file update? So, like how long
does it take to propagate across the
whole project? And we measure the
performance for, you know, various code
bases in CI and that's enough to stop, I
think, like really catastrophic
progressions, but it does require like
right now it requires some vigilance and
like profiling and monitoring and
running benchmarks before each release
to make sure we didn't like, you know,
break something horrendously.
Okay, I see what you're getting at. So,
we talked about laziness and I can see
how laziness would help in terms of
performance. And then we've also now
talked about parallelism. Is there
anything else that either of you would
like to say when it comes to what makes
PyreFly fast?
Danny touched on this and it's a great
way to round out the list,
incrementality.
So, say that we've started an analysis
and we've given you the first round of
of type errors for your project and then
you make a change. We don't want to redo
all of the work for everything
every time you type a single character
in your IDE. So, the other I think major
aspect of the design of PyreFly is is
incrementally updating the analysis when
the code changes.
Okay, so now that we know a little bit
about incrementality, is the idea that
it's like progressively increasing the
scope of the analysis that PyreFly is
going to study? Is that what
incrementality does?
So, what I mean by incrementality, the
way that it works in practice is that as
we do the analysis, and we talked a
little bit about chasing dependencies,
right? So, I reference a name that comes
from an import that comes from another
file. As we resolve those dependencies,
we record that in a dependency graph.
And the dependency graph tracks the
dependencies and then also the reverse
dependencies. So, if I have a file, I
know all the files that depend on me.
So, when I change, what PyreFly does is
it looks at my reverse dependencies and
says, "Okay, now you're invalidated,
too. And you also need to be rechecked."
Okay, I get it. Now, I notice that both
of you are active in the repository for
PyreFly on GitHub. And so, I'd like to
turn our conversation briefly to a
discussion about the governance of
PyreFly and how you at Meta and others
at Meta are helping to build it and
release it as open source, but then also
apply it directly inside of Meta. So,
I'm wondering, can you tell our
listeners a little bit about how you go
about managing PyreFly on GitHub both
internally and externally?
Yeah, so this is one area where
PyreFly's development has differed a lot
from Pyre. Our Pyre was more like it was
built primarily to be a tool at Meta,
and our main users were people at Meta.
And the code was, you know, shared on
GitHub, but, you know, we weren't
necessarily taking a lot of pull
requests or responding to issues like
quickly or making public releases
quickly. PyreFly is has a completely
different model. So, we're making weekly
releases with, you know, detailed
release notes for people outside the
company to consume. We get dozens and
dozens of pull requests every week and
we try to review them in a timely
manner. And we have very active activity
on the issue tracker and we like try
pretty hard to solve issues that were
raised by early adopters and people
outside the company as well. So, like no
longer are people at Meta the primary
user base or the majority of users. Like
PyreFly probably has over a million,
probably more active users in the IDE
every day. Through various editors that
bundle PyreFly like anti-gravity,
Positron, things like that. But also you
can see PyPI downloads. You know, a lot
of people use PyreFly in their CI as
well. So, we're well aware that like
PyreFly is not mainly for
developers at Meta. It's It's designed
to work well with like the broader
Python ecosystem outside the company.
Thanks, that was really helpful. Now, I
know that the Python typing community
has something that's called the
conformance test suite. So, what I'm
wondering is how do you decide what new
feature to add to PyreFly or what bug to
fix? And then how do you track how well
PyreFly does when it comes to this
conformance test suite? Could you share
a little bit more, Sam, about this
topic?
Yeah, so first let me explain what the
conformance test suite is. So, we
talked about how type annotations in
Python are actually part of the Python
language specification. And this is a
really important point and it's what
make One thing that makes Python type
checking really different from say
TypeScript in JavaScript. TypeScript is
an extension of JavaScript, the
JavaScript spec, and does not include
type annotations at all. But in Python
it's it's a part of the language and
there is a council, the Python typing
council, whose which is part of the
overall Python language governance. And
their responsibility is to specify what
these annotations mean. So, part of
their mandate is to maintain this typing
specification and the conformance test
suite, which is a automated like CI kind
of for do type checkers implement the
specification correctly. So, we have
tried very hard and done a lot of work
to pass the conformance test suite. I
believe we just recently passed a 90% of
tests passing, which is a really a big
accomplishment that we're quite proud
of.
As it stands today, the conformance test
suite covers really a small fraction of
what type checkers actually need to do
to work
in practice on real-world code. So,
when it we decide what we're going to
build next,
the conformance test suite is of course
a factor, but the much more important
factor is, "Hey, let's try this on that
corpus of real-world code and see what
kind of errors we find or don't find and
how do we make PyreFly work correctly?"
Okay, I get it. So, if I'm understanding
this the right way, the higher score
that you get on the conformance test
suite, the better job that PyreFly or
other type checkers are doing when it
comes to fulfilling the PEP and the
specification for typing in Python. Is
that the right way for our listeners to
think about this?
Yes, although I mean, like I said, the
conformance test suite doesn't cover a
lot of important things. So, it doesn't
cover anything about type inference. So,
if you write this the very simple
program, x = 1, what does that mean? The
specification does not at this moment
have anything to say about that.
Okay, I get it. Thanks for course
correcting there. So, it's good if you
pass the conformance test suite or have
a higher score for the conformance test
suite, but that still may not really
tell a developer how good of a job pyre
fly or TY or other tools are actually
going to do on their own code base. And
so therefore, they're going to have to
try it out and learn from their own
experiences.
Yeah, I mean, I think that really the
test is to try it out. It's not hard to
try. So, you know, definitely give it a
shot, but that's the best way.
Now, in a moment, we're going to take
one big step back, and in order to help
us to do that, I wanted to take one
moment very quickly to look at this from
the big picture. So, some of our
listeners are already aware of using a
tool like Pytest to run a test suite,
and maybe they've used other types of
tools like linting tools. So, if you
take a big step back, what would you say
pyre fly fits into when it compares to
linting and testing? And how should our
listeners think about using type
checkers and LSPs and test suites and
linters in their overall big picture
Python development process?
So, I think Pyre Fly and type checkers
in general, you know, fit in together
with both runtime tests and linters. I
feel like there's like a perception that
like linters give like non-critical
warnings that, you know, are like best
practices and suggestions, whereas I
think type checkers mostly flag things
that could lead to runtime errors. And
of course, compared to runtime testing,
I think it's useful to have both type
checking and tests. The main benefit of
type checking in addition to tests is
that you kind of you almost get like
100% coverage for free because the type
checker reads all of your code. You
don't have to write explicit test cases
that cover every single branch. And in
addition to the command line type
checking, the way language servers fit
into this is just if you want like a
rich IDE experience, so like to let you
like understand the code better,
navigate your code faster, the language
server helps. And like the reason why
Pyre Fly does both is that, you know,
the information needed to compute the
all the type errors for a project is
kind of like a subset of, you know, what
the language server does. Like the
language server can also in the IDE
gives you all the errors for the
project. So, if you turn that make it a
command line, then you have a command
line type checker. So, if you implement
it as a language server first, you get
both. And the language server can help
both, you know, humans and AI now
because you can have this like MCP
server then the your AI agent can know
that oh, Pyreflite provides these
services. Like it can provide, for
example, like give me the type at this
position. The AI can query Pyreflite for
that information and it's, you know,
more reliable than like the AI having to
do a bunch of like grepping and reading
a bunch of files to try to piece
together the context to get the type of
something.
Thank you, Danny. That was actually
where I was going to go for my final
main question for the show. So, you
mentioned the idea of an AI agent almost
being like in the driver's seat of
Pyreflite. And I wanted to dwell here
kind of in a bigger picture, the future
of Pyreflite perspective. What does it
look like if Pyreflite is now a tool
used by agents as much as it is by an
IDE directly or by a human using the
IDE? Do either of you have thoughts that
you'd like to share on that topic as we
draw our episode to a conclusion?
Yeah, I think this is a really
interesting question and it's one that
we are in the process of figuring out
for ourselves. So, one thing that we're
looking at right now is trying to build
an experimental framework to evaluate
does Pyreflite help an agent succeed at
a given task? So, this is an area of
active research for us. My colleague Jia
Chen has spearheaded a lot of this work
on the team, but you know, it's it's
super interesting and it's it's not
exactly clear, right? I mean, there's a
big, you know, hypothesis that we need
to prove because the agents, you know,
if you've used them, they're pretty good
at figuring out what the code is doing
without much help. So, maybe we can help
the agent be more efficient, use fewer
tokens. Maybe there's, you know, not
that much use for type checking at all
in an agentic world. I think the the
future is not yet written.
Okay, so I'm going to look forward to
both of you helping to write that
future. In our episode today, we've
covered a lot about type checking and
Python programming. And if listeners are
interested in checking out some other
software engineering radio episodes,
we'll link them to those in the show
notes, like episode 589, which was on
property-based testing in Python, and
other episodes that we've done that are
related to packaging management or
FastAPI, or other tooling in Rust, like
episode 622 and 624. With that, I know
we've covered a lot of ground, but Sam
and Danny, is there anything that we've
left out that you wanted to share with
our listeners about PyreFly?
I think we covered quite a lot about,
you know, PyreFly's capabilities. So, I
guess my last thing would be like a call
to action of sorts, like, you know,
please give PyreFly a try. We are still
in beta, but we'll, you know, have our
general release soon. So, please give it
a try in your projects and report any
bugs that you find. We will get back to
you as quickly as we can. You know, if
you have want to engage with PyreFly
maintainers directly, we have a Discord,
and we hold bi-weekly office hours where
you can talk to us directly if you have
questions.
Hey, that's super cool. And in a moment,
Sam, I'm going to turn to you, but since
Danny, you mentioned this call to action
of trying it out, it also made me think
about how PyreFly has something that's
called the PyreFly playground, which
runs directly in our browser. So, Sam,
before I turn it to you, Danny, can you
tell our listeners, what's this
playground about, and how could that fit
into the call to action that you shared?
PyreFlies Playground is a It's a website
on I think pyreflies.org/playground
or sandbox. I don't remember the exact
link, but it runs PyreFlies compiled to
web assembly in your browser, and you
can write small Python programs, and you
can, you know, PyreFlies will check them
in your browser directly and give you
feedback. You can try things like
hovering over things like It's hooked up
to the language server just running in
your browser. And you can even run the
code in using like a browser Python
runtime. I think Pyodide it was. So,
gives you a little like mini browser
environment that lets you test out
PyreFlies without necessarily needing to
download it, but, you know, downloading
and running it is very quickly or very
fast, so it's The sandbox is useful for
playing around, but like, you Yeah.
Actually using it in a real project is
It's not the same thing.
Okay, thanks for that clarification. And
you're right, it is
pyreflies.org/sandbox.
And if listeners want to install the
tool, they can install it with pip or uv
or run it directly with uvx, and then
maybe quickly try it out inside of the
sandbox. At this point, Sam, I wanted to
turn it over to you. Are there other
things that you wanted to share with our
listeners?
Yeah, I think I'd like to, you know,
mirror what Danny said that, you know,
if you haven't tried PyreFlies yet, give
it a spin, find us on GitHub or on
Discord. But I'll also do a shout-out
specifically to Python library
maintainers. If you maintain a library
written in Python that does not provide
types, I think you especially should
consider it. The future of Python, I
hope, will be typed.
And users will expect types from your
library. So, if you haven't made the
switch yet, check it out, and whichever
type checker you use.
Hey, those were great calls to action
for both of you. I hope many of our
listeners will follow up and learn more
about PyreFlies by checking pyrefly.org
and its homepage, including lots of
details about its performance and how to
install it and how you architected and
designed it. Sam and Danny, it has been
super fun for us and our listeners to
learn all about PyreFly. Thank you for
joining Software Engineering Radio.
Thank you, Gregory. It was a blast.
Thanks for having us.
Hey, thanks for being on the episode.
This is Gregory Cap Hammer signing off
for Software Engineering Radio.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
[music] the podcast, including other
episodes, visit our website at
SE-Radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
SE-Radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
[music]
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.
can just copy paste that, put it in the
code and that constructs a data frame in
Polars. So it's very easy to kind of
keep track of which kind of data samples
you're working with, very easy to edit.
And it was functionality like that
combined with asserting frames frame
equal to see if the match was still
there. And that's the something that we
kept on checking, so in case we
accidentally bump something over or it's
it's very easy to accidentally transform
something in a wrong way, especially
when the the paradigms behind the tools
you're using are different. But this
definitely saved I think in the end
ended up saving
quite a lot of times.
Jeroen, is there anything you wanted to
add to the story?
Yeah, yeah, I wanted to say that it
might be good to point out to others who
may want to do something similar, right?
They may have an existing pipeline
written in some language. Let's choose
Pandas again, Python and Pandas.
And if they wanted to convert that into
Polars,
it is important to realize that you
cannot do this on a line-by-line basis
because the two are just so different.
And that is also why Thijs talked about
the input and output rather than
worrying about the individual
transformations or operations that
pandas was doing, we just looked at,
"Okay, what did it start with? What does
it end with? And how can we get there,
you know, from A to B
using something else?"
Thanks for that insight. I know our
listeners have been following along and
they probably have an interest in
learning more about Polars because of
course we haven't covered all of the
details. Could the two of you share a
little bit with our listeners about how
they can learn about your book or learn
more about the parts of the Polars
ecosystem?
Yeah, so we have a website. The book has
a website. It's polarsguide.com.
And on it, you can get the first chapter
for free and you can get to other
interesting resources from that. It's
also how you can get in touch with Thijs
or myself. So, yeah, polarsguide.com.
That's interesting for when you want to
know more about the book. And then there
are of course also there's the Polars
documentation itself, which is
excellent.
The Polars website, I think is the best
hub that connects everything together.
So, if you go to pola.rs,
unfortunately polars.com was already
taken and we have to buy it for 50K, so
that's not going to work.
[laughter]
So, if you go to pola.rs, that's where
you can find way more information. You
you can find your connections to the
user guide which gives a more detailed
explanation of how to work with these
tools with some examples. You can find
the API reference that has the complete
documentation on all the expressions
that there are. I believe during the
writing of the book at one point Jeroen
found out that there's over 300
expressions even. So, I regularly come
on that website as well. And you can
also find more on the the offerings that
Polars had because we recently started a
a cloud product because we noticed
there's a demand for distributed engine
as well. And that's something that we're
heavily building on right now.
All right. This has really been an
engaging and informative conversation.
And as we draw the episode to a
conclusion, I'd like to turn to each of
you individually. Is there either a new
topic that we haven't covered that you
wanted to very briefly highlight? Or do
you have a call to action for our
listeners so that they can get more
involved with Polars and the Polar
ecosystem in data engineering?
I would say that great way to, you know,
become part of the Polars community is
to join the Discord server. You know,
it's very welcoming. No matter what your
level is.
And you can ask questions there.
Interact with others and people are
really helpful. And
you know, then give it a spin.
All right. That was awesome. Thijs,
anything else you wanted to share in
conclusion?
Yeah, so the main thing from the Polar
side that we've been working on is
really becoming a unified API for not
only being like a a small single node
data frame library, but to also go all
the way to scaling up to big data. And
that's that's something that we're
heavily investing in now. So, like I
said, there's the the Polar Polar cloud
side of things and even on premises if
you want to run it on your own
Kubernetes cluster so your data stays
safe wherever you want to keep it. We're
building heavily on products that can
scale all the way there and are already
defeating Spark in terms of performance
with managed Spark solutions. So, we
strive to keep being the performance
leader on any scale at this point.
Thank you. That sounds super cool. We'll
make sure to link all of our listeners
to everything that we've mentioned in
the episode, so you're welcome to check
the show notes. At this point, Thijs and
Jeroen, thank you so much for the
conversation. It was great to chat with
you both today.
Thank you for having us. It was great.
Thank you.
Hey, you're welcome. And this is now
Gregory Caphammer signing off for
Software Engineering Radio.
[music]
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast, including other episodes,
visit our website at SE-Radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter,
[music]
or through our Slack channel at
SE-Radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
[music]
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
[music]
Thanks for listening.